<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Zippel Lab @ OSU</title>
    <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zippelsf.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 15:02:09 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zippelsf.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>WFIP3</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/wfip3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 15:02:09 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/wfip3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 3rd  Wind Forecast Improvement Project (WFIP3), sponsored by the U.S. Department of Energy, seeks to improve our understanding of the physics of the atmosphere and ocean that dictate the structure and variability of the wind resource within the Marine Atmospheric Boundary Layer (MABL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information contact the project lead: Anthony Kirincich at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:akirincich@whoi.edu&#34;&gt;akirincich@whoi.edu&lt;/a&gt;, or check out the project&amp;rsquo;s website at WHOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www2.whoi.edu/site/wfip3/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www2.whoi.edu/site/wfip3/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sofar Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/sofar-collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 15:01:58 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/sofar-collaboration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m working with folks at Sofar Ocean to test a new iteration of Spotter buoys. An ongoing problem in air/sea interactions is global estimates of air/sea turbulent heat fluxes. These can be estimated using &amp;ldquo;bulk&amp;rdquo; algorithms with measurements of winds, sea surface temperature, air temperature, relative hummidity,  atmospheric pressure, and rain. While some of these quantities can be measured globally from space, near-surface air temperature and humidity remain a challenge. We are testing some new sensors on Spotter buoys to help address this data gap. My group will help deploy 5 new prototype Spotters in Fall 2023 at the Air Sea Interaction Tower (ASIT) south of Martha&amp;rsquo;s Vineyard. We will test data from the new buoys against high-quality meterological measurements made from the tower. This location is particularly appealing due to the stable nature of this offshore research station, which allows for direct measurement of turbulent fluxes without having to deal with the motion of ships and buoys which complicates flux measurements. In addition, ASIT is cabled to shore with a steady supply of power and a fiber optic cable for data transmission so that we don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about power usage and batteries, and we are able to &amp;ldquo;talk&amp;rdquo; to the instruments in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salinity And Stratification at the Sea Ice Edge (SASSIE)</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/sassie/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 17:03:34 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/sassie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sea ice extent in the Arctic Ocean has declined dramatically over the past decades. Autumn ice advance is slower and occurs later, while summer ice retreat is faster and occurs earlier. The result is a lengthening open-water period each year, leading to changes in air-sea heat and momentum fluxes, the freshwater cycle, surface albedo feedbacks, primary production, and regional and global climate as well as human and ecological health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our experiment will examine how summer ice melt evolves into and is inexorably linked with autumn sea ice advance, focusing on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantifying the salinity anomalies generated by melting ice, how they evolve in time, and how they affect stratification, sea surface temperature (SST), and subsequent ice advance;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploring these processes using a series of model experiments; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collecting data to enable improved satellite sea surface salinity (SSS) retrievals in polar oceans, and linking the in situ salinity signals with those observed from satellites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SASSIE will address its science themes in a multi-scale in situ, airborne, satellite, and modeling experiment. The primary aim of the field campaign is to capture the upper ocean structure during the transition from summer sea ice retreat to autumn sea ice advance. We will quantify the strength, size, and depth of fresh near-surface anomalies resulting from melting ice; the horizontal and vertical structure of those fresh anomalies as they evolve due to air-sea fluxes and waves, ocean currents and mixing; and the ocean conditions and the presence of sea ice as it begins to form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the main project site here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://salinity.oceansciences.org/sassie.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://salinity.oceansciences.org/sassie.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Air/Sea Fluxes Mediated by Pressure Work</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/pressure-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 15:22:22 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/pressure-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Drs. Seth Zippel, Malcolm Scully, and  Jim Edson are seeking a doctoral student for an NSF-funded project to study turbulence in the oceanic and atmospheric boundary layers. We are hoping to understand the role of ocean waves, wave breaking, and turbulent pressure in atmosphere and ocean exchanges, which are central to understanding air/sea transfer of heat, gasses, and momentum. We will conduct two field experiments with a tower in Pamlico sound, NC, collecting wave, turbulence, and pressure data on both the atmosphere and water sides of the boundary. These findings will help improve our fundamental understanding of air/sea interactions, which are central to weather, climate, and upper ocean transport for biota, plastics, and other tracers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smart Oceans 2020</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/smart-oceans-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 15:06:47 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/smart-oceans-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
