<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Seth Zippel (he/him) | Zippel Lab @ OSU</title>
    <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/authors/szippel/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zippelsf.github.io/authors/szippel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Seth Zippel (he/him)</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 17:13:29 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zippelsf.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Seth Zippel (he/him)</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/authors/szippel/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>WFIP3 ASIT Mast Deployment</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/wfip3-asit-deployment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 17:13:29 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/wfip3-asit-deployment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month we deployed a suite of sensors on WHOI&amp;rsquo;s ASIT (Air/Sea Interaction Tower) as part of a DOE-funded project to improve offshore wind forecasts. The focus of this deployment was to install sensors to measure and characterize the marine boundary layer. Several sensors are already maintained at ASIT, and we added additional capability by installing a 30-ft mast fixed to the diving board, the human-walkable platform at roughly 35ft above the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We transported the mast to ASIT using WHOI&amp;rsquo;s R/V Tioga, strapping it horizontally to the back of the A-frame. The mast was too tall to fit upright on the Tioga without hitting the bottom of the diving board, and transporting it horizontally allowed us more maneuverability when picking the mast onto the tower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;tioga.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a challenging pick. With winds much higher than were forecast for the day, the Tioga was unable to hold position for long underneath ASIT&amp;rsquo;s diving board. This gave our team very little time to grab the hoisting line with a boathook, shackle the hoisting line to our lifting bridle on the mast, and hoist the mast clear of the Tioga&amp;rsquo;s A-frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;after_pick.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the mast clear of the Tioga, we had to rotate it upright and pull it above the diving board to install sensors which were removed to avoid possible damage during transfer from Tioga to ASIT. We ran into a small hiccup when the mast started to rotate due to the weight of the booms, but due to some quick thinking from the field team we were able to rotate the mast back into the intended position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;diving_board.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately all of our sensors were working as expected and communicating with our data logger when powered on. Now, all that was needed were a few final tasks to further secure the mast in position, and to make sure our cables were fixed in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;featured.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because ASIT has a fiber-optic cable running along the sea floor connecting it to shore, we can check the data in real time. A good first check for data quality is to compare it against proven models and/or previously accepted data. So far, the data from the mast look like they are in agreement with &amp;ldquo;bulk&amp;rdquo; methods for determining air/sea fluxes of momentum and heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;WFIP3-MAST_bulk_vs_DCFS.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;Title&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SASSIE Data Available</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/sassie-data-live/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 12:48:26 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/sassie-data-live/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Data and code for SASSIE is available! Check out what is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://salinity.oceansciences.org/sassie-data.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WFIP3</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/wfip3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 15:02:09 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/wfip3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 3rd  Wind Forecast Improvement Project (WFIP3), sponsored by the U.S. Department of Energy, seeks to improve our understanding of the physics of the atmosphere and ocean that dictate the structure and variability of the wind resource within the Marine Atmospheric Boundary Layer (MABL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information contact the project lead: Anthony Kirincich at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:akirincich@whoi.edu&#34;&gt;akirincich@whoi.edu&lt;/a&gt;, or check out the project&amp;rsquo;s website at WHOI: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www2.whoi.edu/site/wfip3/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www2.whoi.edu/site/wfip3/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sofar Buoys at ASIT</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/sofar-buoys-at-asit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 14:45:01 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/sofar-buoys-at-asit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m working with folks at Sofar Ocean to test a new iteration of Spotter buoys. An ongoing problem in air/sea interactions is global estimates of air/sea turbulent heat fluxes. These can be estimated using &amp;ldquo;bulk&amp;rdquo; algorithms with measurements of winds, sea surface temperature, air temperature, relative hummidity,  atmospheric pressure, and rain. While some of these quantities can be measured globally from space, near-surface air temperature and humidity remain a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are testing some new sensors on Spotter buoys to help address this data gap. My group helped deploy 5 new prototype Spotters in early September at the Air Sea Interaction Tower (ASIT) south of Martha&amp;rsquo;s Vineyard, where we will test the new buoys against high-quality meterological measurements made from the tower. This location is particularly appealing due to the stable nature of this offshore research station, which allows for direct measurement of turbulent fluxes without having to deal with the motion of ships and buoys which complicates flux measurements. In addition, ASIT is cabled to shore with a steady supply of power and a fiber optic cable for data transmission so that we don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about power usage and batteries, and we are able to &amp;ldquo;talk&amp;rdquo; to the instruments in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future analysis will test how well the new Spotters are able to capture the turbulent heat fluxes and rain rates with their newly integrated sensors.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moved to OSU!</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/moved-to-osu/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 14:41:05 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/moved-to-osu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve moved to Oregon State! While I will miss Woods Hole, I am so excited to join the wonderfull folks at CEOAS, and can&amp;rsquo;t wait to start this new chapter of my career.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BBASIT Spring Updates</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/bbasit-spring-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 10:40:05 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/bbasit-spring-updates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After a long year of planning and logistical hurdles, including a change of location from North Carolina to Buzzards Bay, we successfully deployed our air-sea interaction tower this April. The tower, dubbed BBASIT (Buzzards Bay Air-Sea Interaction Tower), is a 70 ft tall open-frame tower in 40 ft of water that serves as a stable platform for a host of meteorological and oceanic instrumentation as part of an NSF-funded project to study turbulence near the air/water interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dense vertical array of ocean and atmospheric sensors are measuring winds, currents, waves, temperature, and turbulence (to name a few). We hope that the data from BBASIT will illuminate how kinetic energy is transferred from the air to surface waves, and from waves to the water below. These energy transfers are central to how the air, the waves, and the water are linked, which impacts the air/water transfer of heat, gasses and momentum. All of these exchanges are important components for predictions of weather and climate. We hope our findings here can improve how these weather and climate models calculate air/sea transfers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salinity And Stratification at the Sea Ice Edge (SASSIE)</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/sassie/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 17:03:34 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/sassie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sea ice extent in the Arctic Ocean has declined dramatically over the past decades. Autumn ice advance is slower and occurs later, while summer ice retreat is faster and occurs earlier. The result is a lengthening open-water period each year, leading to changes in air-sea heat and momentum fluxes, the freshwater cycle, surface albedo feedbacks, primary production, and regional and global climate as well as human and ecological health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our experiment will examine how summer ice melt evolves into and is inexorably linked with autumn sea ice advance, focusing on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantifying the salinity anomalies generated by melting ice, how they evolve in time, and how they affect stratification, sea surface temperature (SST), and subsequent ice advance;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploring these processes using a series of model experiments; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collecting data to enable improved satellite sea surface salinity (SSS) retrievals in polar oceans, and linking the in situ salinity signals with those observed from satellites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SASSIE will address its science themes in a multi-scale in situ, airborne, satellite, and modeling experiment. The primary aim of the field campaign is to capture the upper ocean structure during the transition from summer sea ice retreat to autumn sea ice advance. We will quantify the strength, size, and depth of fresh near-surface anomalies resulting from melting ice; the horizontal and vertical structure of those fresh anomalies as they evolve due to air-sea fluxes and waves, ocean currents and mixing; and the ocean conditions and the presence of sea ice as it begins to form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the main project site here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://salinity.oceansciences.org/sassie.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://salinity.oceansciences.org/sassie.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smart Oceans Summary</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/smart-oceans-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:08 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/smart-oceans-summary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks all for attending Smart Oceans 2020! &lt;a href=&#34;https://zippelsf.github.io/files/smartoceans.pdf&#34;&gt;See the excecutive summary here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>O2 Flux at WBNERR</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/o2-flux-at-wbnerr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 09:45:01 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/post/o2-flux-at-wbnerr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week, Matt Long and I are testing a new theory we have about how much oxygen can be transfered between the air and water in estuaries and ponds. Currently, nost scientists apply a formula for this transfer (called the gas transfer velocity, because it has units of m/s) based only on the wind speed. This works in the open ocean where waves have room to grow, and are typically in lock step with the local wind. In small ponds and estuaries, the distance wind can blow over water (called fetch) limits the growth of waves, and changes how much turbulence is at the air/water boundary. These smaller waves and modified turbulence levels then change how much gas can be exchanged across the interface. We are collecting data this week at Waquoit Bay to test a new formula that includes fetch in estimating the gas tranfer velocity. Our hope is that this will improve estimates of oxygen flux in nearshore regions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Air/Sea Fluxes Mediated by Pressure Work</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/pressure-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 15:22:22 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/pressure-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Drs. Seth Zippel, Malcolm Scully, and  Jim Edson are seeking a doctoral student for an NSF-funded project to study turbulence in the oceanic and atmospheric boundary layers. We are hoping to understand the role of ocean waves, wave breaking, and turbulent pressure in atmosphere and ocean exchanges, which are central to understanding air/sea transfer of heat, gasses, and momentum. We will conduct two field experiments with a tower in Pamlico sound, NC, collecting wave, turbulence, and pressure data on both the atmosphere and water sides of the boundary. These findings will help improve our fundamental understanding of air/sea interactions, which are central to weather, climate, and upper ocean transport for biota, plastics, and other tracers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smart Oceans 2020</title>
      <link>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/smart-oceans-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 15:06:47 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zippelsf.github.io/project/smart-oceans-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
